<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deceit brought to day-light: in an ansvver to Thomas Collier, vvhat he hath declared in a book called, A dialogue between a minister, and a Christian: but by his fruits hee is tryed and found to be neither. In which answer his lies are returned for the founder to prove; his errors laid open, read, and reproved, and he found to be the same in deeds which he accuses the Quakers to be in words. / Published in short for the souls sake, that the simplicity may bee preserved from the subtilty, lest any should believe lies, and so be given up to delusion, and bee damned, by a lover of truth, called, James Naylor.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E885_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168397</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89832)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E885[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deceit brought to day-light: in an ansvver to Thomas Collier, vvhat he hath declared in a book called, A dialogue between a minister, and a Christian: but by his fruits hee is tryed and found to be neither. In which answer his lies are returned for the founder to prove; his errors laid open, read, and reproved, and he found to be the same in deeds which he accuses the Quakers to be in words. / Published in short for the souls sake, that the simplicity may bee preserved from the subtilty, lest any should believe lies, and so be given up to delusion, and bee damned, by a lover of truth, called, James Naylor.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 2, 4-28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.L. for Giles Calvert at the black-Spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Collier, Thomas.  A dialogue between a minister of the Gospel, and an enquiring Christian.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691. --  Dialogue between a minister of the Gospel, and an enquiring Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168397:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DECEIT Brought to DAY-LIGHT: IN AN ANSWER TO Thomas Collier, VVhat he hath declared in a book called, <hi>A Dialogue between a Miniſter, and a Chriſtian:</hi> But by his fruits hee is tryed and found to be neither. In which Anſwer his lies are returned for the Founder to prove; his Errors laid open, read, and reproved, and he found to be the ſame in deeds which he accuſes the Quakers to be in words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed in ſhort for the ſouls ſake, that the ſimplicity may bee preſerved from the ſubtilty, leſt any ſhould believe lies, and ſo be given up to deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bee damned, By a Lover of Truth, called,</hi> James Naylor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They have made lies their refuge, and under falſhood have they hid themſelves; but judgement is laid to the Line, and righteouſneſs to the Plummet, and the hail ſhall ſweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters ſhall overflow the hiding place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. L.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black-Spread-Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168397:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168397:2"/>
            <head>The EPISTLE to the READER. AND TO THOMAS COLLIER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His generation with ſpeed fulfils its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of wickedneſs, againſt the ſeed of God, till the ſeed of <hi>Eſau</hi> become a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation for ever, and the Armies of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> with their men of warr, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from all quarters in defiance of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> til there be not a man left to handle the ſword: We are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey to the ſlanderous tongue, and are made as a mark for the wicked, againſt which they bend their bowe, and ſhoots their arrowes, even bitter words of lies and reproaches, more then may bee numbred; but the wickedneſs of the wicked ſhal ſlay him; and his tranſgreſſion ſhall fall upon his owne head; for though they ſtrive, yet to no purpoſe, for the Warrier loſes his hand in the day of battel, and his ſtrength becomes weakneſs, and his wiſdom is turned into folly; and even this man <hi>Thomas Collier,</hi> hath helped up the meaſure of his generation, and is no whit ſhort, but the rather exceeding ſome of his
<pb facs="tcp:168397:3"/>
Brethren in lies and ſlanders, and reproaches, and his teſtimony hath he given againſt the Lord, and his mite hath he caſt in unto <hi>Babylon's</hi> confuſion, to make up the number of the Beaſt in the warre againſt the Lamb, againſt which the whole body and train of darkneſs, from the head to the tail, is joyned in the agreement of hell, and is now come forth in the power and authority of the Beaſt; they are gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Lord, that they may be ſcattered by the whirlwind of his wrath, and they are riſen that they may be broken to pieces, and they have ſpoken that they may be condemned out of their own <hi>mouths</hi> and this man with many of his brethren, is juſtly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the pit which he digged for another, and the ſnare hath trapped his own foot; and he is the man who is found and proved (in a high degree) guilty of that wickedneſs and tranſgreſſion whereof he falſly accuſes us, and the reproach ſtands upon his owne head, which he hath thought to lay upon the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: VVhat? art thou among the reſt, fled to lies for refuge, as thy laſt defence? Is this the end of thy profeſsion, and of thy high notions, who was once mounted up into the air among the wandering ſtars, carried for a time as a cloud with the tempeſt; but now art thou fallen into the earth, becauſe there was no abiding place for thee, and art turned again into the beggarly rudiments of the world, where the chains of darkneſs compaſſes thee about till the Judgement of the great day, for which thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and thy lies are numbred to go into the pit together. In this preſent Anſwer unto thy fooliſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented diſcourſe, he that hath underſtanding, may
<pb facs="tcp:168397:3"/>
read thy ſhame and confuſion; thou art not found onely upon ſecret ſearch, but manifeſtly thy impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence appears, and much need not be ſaid, but onely thy lies are ſent back to thee in a groſs ſum gathered up from thy mouth, to ſeek a witneſs from thee of what thou haſt aſſerted, thou haſt ſlandered, but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no evidence, and haſt made thy ſelf a tranſgreſſor of the law, which would thee to do as thou would be done unto, and till then we do wait, or elſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do let them reſt upon thy own head, as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them; and thereof ſhalt thou have ſhame and reproach in the ſight of all juſt men, in this preſent world, &amp; vengeance in the ſight of God in the world to come; and in that day ſhalt thou confeſs unto thy condemnation to be juſt, in the preſence of the <hi>Lord God:</hi> How eaſie a thing is it for thee to make a lye, and then to diſprove it? But this is not the way to prove us deceivers; for our doctrine and converſation ſhall bear witneſs for us in the ſight of men, and by the light in every mans conſcience to bee witneſſed; and unto the living God we do appeal for judgment, and leaves it unto his day; and for this purpoſe haſt thou appeared againſt us that thy folly might appear unto all men; and thou in thy ſecret envy (which hath lodged in thy heart) might be known unto all; who hath travelled to bring forth wickedneſs; and thou ſhalt be filled with thy own wayes, and muſt receive the juſt reward thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>the 3 of the fifth moneth 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>E. Burrough.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168397:4"/>
            <head>DECEIT Brought to DAY-LIGHT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riend, Though thou be late with this thy work, yet one of <hi>Gog's</hi> Army thou muſt appear, and having both Queſtions and Anſwers in thine own hand, thou haſt made up a heap of lies and confuſion to caſt in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, even ſuch filthy things out of thy own unclean ſpirit haſt thou caſt upon the truth, as honeſty would have been aſhamed to utter, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of that which thou knowes nought of but by hearſay, the life being that which thou art ſhut out of, and all the image-makers in the Nations: Thou ſayeſt our principles are but the principles of the old Ranters, which is as far from them both in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and practice as light and darkneſs, which clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewes thy ignorance of us, and envy to us: it's true, the Rantersprinciples thou haſt known, and their practice alſo, and I ſhould be glad to ſee thee as clear from them as thou would make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thou art, but our principle thou knowes not,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168397:4"/>
that eye is blind, with which thou ſhouldſt ſee it, or the life from which it ariſes, and therefore the Lyar is up in thee foaming out thy own ſhame, ſpeaking things from the euill of thine own heart, which thou canſt not prove, nor make appear, things utterly falſe and untrue, which we can ſay before the Lord, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entred into us to believe or declare, which thou layes downe as our principles, and that ſpirit would ſay as much by our practice; but that thou would not be ſeen openly to be a lyar.</p>
            <p>And left thou should ſay I wrong thee, I shall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out ſome of thy lyes thou haſt falſly ſlandered us with in this booke, and ſend thee them backe to the Founder to prove, if thou canſt, or own thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for a falſe accuſer; and by that time thy Lies be ſent back, the reſt of thy book that concerns us will be ſoon anſwered. Thy lies be ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, thou ſayeſt, that all our principles are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions.</p>
            <p>That we hold not any one principle of truth truly as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>That we forſake the true way decreed of God for the attaining of Juſtification, which is by faith in Chriſt crucified.</p>
            <p>That we call Juſtification by faith in Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, carnal.</p>
            <p>That we have ſet up an other way to attain juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that is, by quaking.</p>
            <p>That we have outed Chriſt in his great worke of Juſtification.</p>
            <p>That we have trampled under foot the blood of the covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168397:5"/>That we have counted the blood of the covenant a thing too unholy for us to look at for Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>That we diſown <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his aſcention, interceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the works of his Mediatorſhip.</p>
            <p>That we have found another way to go to God then by <hi>Chriſt</hi> Mediator.</p>
            <p>That we diſown <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Authority.</p>
            <p>That we will not ſubmit to <hi>Christ</hi> in his Word.</p>
            <p>That inſtead of hearkning to the Voice of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Scripture, we hearken to, and follow after the Voice of Satan.</p>
            <p>That the beſt we hearken to is but our own deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hearts.</p>
            <p>That we call the voice of Satan in our own deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hearts the Voice of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we do obey the voice of Satan in our own hearts, though contrary to all rules of God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>That we diſown the coming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> from heaven</p>
            <p>That we diſown Chriſt's Kingdome which is the great and bleſſed promiſe of the Goſpel: the faith and hope of Saints.</p>
            <p>That we diſown the Reſurrection of the dead in the ſecond appearance of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>That we diſown the eternal life with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That we own our ſelves to be perfect.</p>
            <p>That we own our ſelves to be free from ſin, entred into a ſtate of Juſtification, not by faith in Chriſt, but by our own righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>That we own neither ſalvation nor damnation of any perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168397:5"/>That our principles are but the principles of the old Ranters.</p>
            <p>That the devil hath hemm'd us in with a pretence of our own infallibility.</p>
            <p>That we will not admit of no ſober Diſcourſe, nor bring our principles to tryal of Scripture.</p>
            <p>That railing Accuſations, and hiddeous names, is the ſtrength of our Arguments for our way.</p>
            <p>That amongſt all the falſe wayes of Satan, there is none more pernicious and dangerous then we are.</p>
            <p>That we undermine the whole body of truth.</p>
            <p>That our way makes an end of Chriſt in his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Offices, Power, and being as a man all at once; and ſo makes an end of Juſtification and Salvation.</p>
            <p>That we make an end of the Authority of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as a rule.</p>
            <p>That we deny the birth from above by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>That we hold it as our great principle, that the light that is in all men is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That we turn from the light of Chriſt ſhining in the Scriptures, to follow our imaginations and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies inſtead of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That we do but talk of the Name of Chriſt for a juggle and a cheat.</p>
            <p>That under the Name of Chriſt we ſtob him.</p>
            <p>That we lay aſide the Man <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> our lord, as a thing of nought.</p>
            <p>That under a pretence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> within, we take an advantage to murther the true <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we are guilty of the great and damnable ſin
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168397:6"/>
of unbelief in <hi>Christ</hi> crucified for ſin, the way, the truth and the life.</p>
            <p>That we ſet up another ſalvation of our own with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us:</p>
            <p>That we ſacrifice to our own Nets.</p>
            <p>That we proclaim, that all that own Juſtification through Faith in the blood of the covenant are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>That we own it as a principle, not to ſubmit to any word or law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> written in Scripture.</p>
            <p>That we trample under foot the Laws and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt recorded in Sctipture.</p>
            <p>That we judge all thoſe that walk therein to be Enemies.</p>
            <p>That we proclaim our own righteouſneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>That we condemn the poor humble ſouls for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanes, that live in a ſight and ſenſe of themſelves.</p>
            <p>That we ſhut up the kingdom of heaven, and will not go in, nor ſuffer others that are entering.</p>
            <p>That we will not enter unleſs we may enter by our own righteouſneſs, and not by the blood of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p>That we leave the weighty things of Faith and Obedience to the Laws and Ordinances of Chriſt undone, as vile and contemptible.</p>
            <p>That we make God a lyar.</p>
            <p>That we deſtroy civil curteſie, as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it.</p>
            <p>That we level all conditions and relations, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all things common upon this accompt.</p>
            <p>That under a pretence of perfection, we bring
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168397:6"/>
forth a Religion made up of infidelity, diſobedience, hypocriſie, pride, trampling under foot the blood of the covenant, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That we are guilty of that Hell-born ſin of lying and deceit.</p>
            <p>Theſe abominable folſhoods (with many more ſuch like) haſt thou uttered out of thy boſome; theſe lyes comes with as much impudence and boldneſs as though thou ſhould never be called into judgement for them hereafter, nor put to prove them now, much like to that ſcolding ſpirit which ſticks not to call thief and whore freely, but when they ſhould prove it falls on their own head; this is not the firſt time this venome hath been caſt upon us, by that brood whcreof thou art; yet to us it ſticks not, it comes no neerer the truth, but out of the lyars boſome, that it may return upon the lyars head; ſo take theſe again and prove us (whom thou haſr ſlandered therewith) to be guilty, as thou haſt ſaid, or own thy condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a falſe accuſer before God and all the world before whom thou haſt ſlandered us falſly, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his light in thy conſcience, to which thou art an enemie, leſt they remain with thee till the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful day of Gods wrath againſt the lyar and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And now thy lies being ſent back to the founder, the greateſt part of thy book (as to what thou haſt writ againſt us) is anſwered and come to nought; ſo the foundation is diſcovered on which thy worke ſtands; take away the lye and thou art diſarmed.</p>
            <p>But now ſeeing thou haſt falſly charged us to ſet up wayes to ſalvation, which are not the man <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168397:7"/>
Ieſus,</hi> I ſhall make it appear to be thy own work to ſet up a way to <hi>ſalvation</hi> to which thou would binde men, which is neither the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> nor his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſhall not imitate thee therein, by ſaying thou doſt ſo, and ſo leave it; but firſt I ſhall prove it, and then let it ſtand on thy head for ever, unleſs thou deny thy error, and repent: thus I prove it.</p>
            <p>In thy 15 page thou limits the converſion of all that have been, are, or ſhall be converted ſince the Apoſtles time, to that written by the Apoſtles, and left to after-generations; and in thy 17 page thou affirms it to be the abſolute rule of Saints.</p>
            <p>And this letter of the <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Apoſtles writing,</hi> I deny to be the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> and that it is not the Spirit thy ſelf confeſſes in <hi>pag.</hi> 22. in theſe words, where thou ſayeſt, <hi>to ſay that the Scripture is Spirit that diſcovers much ignorance, and indeed ſuch look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it with an idolatrous eye,</hi> and ſayeth further, <hi>that the Spirit of God is alwayes diſtinguiſhed from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My own I prove thus; The Man Chriſt Jeſus aſcended, but the Letter of the Apoſtles did not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, nor could before it was written; for then it was no letter.</p>
            <p>Again, if the writings of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> be the man <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> then we have part of him viſible here on earth, and part is loſt, which few will ſay.</p>
            <p>Again, the viſible part of the Apoſtles writings is paper and ink; but ſo is not the viſible part of the man Chriſt Jeſus; more might be ſaid which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proves that the Apoſtles writing is not the man
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168397:7"/>
Chriſt Jeſus; and thou haſt confeſſed they are not the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and yet thou affirms them to bee the abſolute rule of Saints, and way of converſion, ſo as God may not convert any but by them, which he hath ſaid of nothing but Chriſt himſelf; ſo that if thou have not ſet up an abſolute rule that is not <hi>Chriſts</hi>'s, and bound God to work by, and all people to believe in a way of converſion and ſalvation that is not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in fleſh nor ſpirit, as is cleerly proved, let the truth in all conſciences judge, and ſee if the liar bee not fallen into the pit he hath digged for the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
            <p>Further, let the wiſe judge if thou have not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by concluded all damned, who have lived and dyed ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, and have not heard the Letter written by the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> for if all that have been, are, or ſhall be converted ſince the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, muſt be by their writings, then who hath not their writings cannot be converted nor brought to God.</p>
            <p>Thus hath thou limited God to a Bible to convert by, and condemned all that have not one, or heard one; and with ſuch blinde ſtuff thou goes on to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our errors, but cannot ſee thy own blindneſs.</p>
            <p>Further thou haſt ſet up a new way of converting ſouls, then by which <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God was converted, and hath bound God to it; for they was not converted by the writings of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> before they was, or they that writ them, and ſo art laying another foundation then was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and was the ſoundation of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who was converted before the letter of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> was; and ſo art he thou tells on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168397:8"/>
who art preaching another Goſpel, and accurſed.</p>
            <p>And now that I have proved thee one who art ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up another way to <hi>ſalvation</hi> that is not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; ſetting up one to rule that is not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo art <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> I ſhall charge thee therewith till thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſhall add this thy falſe doctrine to the reſt of thy lies, by which I deny thy ſpirit to be of <hi>God,</hi> thy book, thy lies, thy confuſion, thy feigned words, and thy antichriſtian doctrine, and all thou ſayeſt, I do declare to proceed from the Spirit of the falſe Prophet, the lyar and ſlanderer, and one that goes about to ſet up a way and rule abſolute which is not Chriſt, and ſo another Goſpel, and foundation, and no modeſty can blame me for charging thy falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine upon thy head, being firſt thus plainly proved; and haddeſt thou thus proved before thou had ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, thou had ſhewed more of Gods wiſdome, and leſs of thy own wickedneſs; but the lyar hath been thy tongue for lies like a bow with which thy bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els muſt be filled, yet canſt thou not enter the truth, but thy arrows are driven back on thy own head.</p>
            <p>And as that ſpirit of lies hath its enmity againſt Chriſt, and would ſet up another; ſo it doth oppoſe his light which is the light of the world; and thou heaps up a deal of confuſion to diſprove the witneſs that <hi>Iohn</hi> bare of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 9. who ſaith, <hi>This is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> and this light <hi>Iohn</hi> came to bear witneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>that all men through him might believe, verſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 7. and this he ſaith was in the beginning, and Chriſt ſaith <hi>Iohns</hi> witneſs was true, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 33. but ſaith the lyar, that is but the common natural light that lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168397:8"/>
man that cometh into the world, and is not able to lead to God; and thus they who likes thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better then <hi>Iohn</hi>'s or Chriſt's, they may believe thee, and deny Chriſt and his Miniſters; blinde guides, how are you like to tell what the light will do or not do, who have been oppoſers of it ever ſince it was preached, but hath not followed it to the end? are you like to know whether it leads? did you ever follow it at all? if ſo, what evil hath it led you to? you confeſs it reproves and manifeſts ſinne, and doth not the apoſtle preach this for the light of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 13, 14. but you have an imagination that Chriſt is the light onely to inlighten you that call your ſelves believers; but who muſt inlighten the reſt? Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the light of the world,</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>I am the light of ſuch a form, or ſuch a people,</hi> who are of a ſelf-ſeparation; but, <hi>I am the light of the world, he that followes me ſhall have the light of life;</hi> but you who never followed it ſaith, <hi>there is not life in following it;</hi> ſo your blinde teſtimony who were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the <hi>light</hi> of the world ſtand againſt the teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony of Chriſt and the children of <hi>light, John</hi> 8. 12.</p>
            <p>But ſaiſt thou, <hi>if this be true, that Chriſt lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that cometh into the world, which light being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heed unto, will lead to God, then Chriſt died in vain, and in vain hath he ſaid,</hi> I <hi>am the way, the truth and the life;</hi> which is as much as if thou had ſaid, <hi>if Chriſt be the light of the world which lighteth every one which cometh into the world and leads to God; in vain did hee come into the world to teſtifie the ſame in preaching and ſuffering (without which it could not have been maniſeſt and believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168397:9"/>But your blindneſs hath been ſo cleerly laid open, and the light proved, even that which is the light of the world, to be the way to the Father the truth and the life, as I need not ſay much to thy blinde oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, onely take theſe two Scriptures, and ſhame with thy blindneſs, who would perſwade people that the light of the world is not the way, the truth, and the life; or that there is any other way but the light of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 6. if theſe be one then art thou blinde; and if not one, then how ſhould thou ſpeak truth? who ſaid, I <hi>am the light of the World, the way, the truth and the life; no man cometh to the father but by me;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> who ſaith, <hi>This is the true light; Joh.</hi> 1. 9. So now let all judge who have the light in them, whether I am in the error who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth what the Letter ſaith, that Chriſt alone is the true light, the way, the truth and the life; and that this is the true light that lighteth every one that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the world, and ſo owns Chriſt of whom the letter teſtifies; or thou, who ſaith; The letter is the abſolute rule, and this light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to God without the Letter, and ſo limits God and denies him who was the way before the Apoſtles was, or wrote the letter, and would make people believe that the writing of the Letter had taken the office of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and were now become abſolute in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, inlightning, and converting to God; and ſo you are become Miniſters of the Letter, and denies the Spirit to be able to convert to God without the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſo a contrary Spirit hath poſſeſſed you then was in the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who was Miniſters of the Spirit and not of the Letter; and ſo contrary fruits are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168397:9"/>
brought forth; and this your oppoſition of the light is but that you may appear to be the blinde guides Chriſt foretold of, and by your fruits you muſt be known; Did ever Miniſter of Chriſt preach againſt the leaſt light of Chriſt, and ſay it was not ſufficient to lead to God, or that none ſhould never be converted but by the letter? Did ever Miniſter of Chriſt preach againſt Perfection as thou doeſt and thy brethren, who ſayes thou doeſt not believe that Perfection is attainable here; thou may as well ſay Chriſt is not attainable here, nor Faith? doeſt not thou here mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter againſt the end of Chriſts miniſtery, and that for which he ſent them forth, which was for the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſaints, and that they might preſent every man perfect in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus? Eph.</hi> 4. 11: 12: 13. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1. 28. and this thou miniſters againſt, and ſayeſt thou canſt not believe it; and adds a lye to thy unbelief, ſaying its an eſtate no where held forth in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as attainable here; and ſo would make God a lyar and the Scripture alſo. As for inſtance; God ſaid <hi>Iobe</hi> was a perfect man; <hi>Iob</hi> 1. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Iob</hi> 8. 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 37. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 15. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 2. with other Scriptures, too many here to mention, which all witneſs thee to belye God and the Scriptures, and to be no Miniſter for Chriſt, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever of his Miniſtry, who art againſt perfection and cannot believe it; this is a fruit of Antichriſt, &amp; none of Chrſts Miniſters, but they believed it and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which thou preaches againſt: And ſo by thy fruits thou art known and thy generation, as Chriſt hath ſaid you ſhould: But to cover thy ſelf thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, its the duty of every one to preſs after perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168397:10"/>
ſo they muſt preſs after that which thou believes not, nor would have them to believ, ſo they muſt pres after that which they believe muſt never attain here: What ſort is this preſſing of, which is againſt faith? yet this confuſion is thy Doctrine, for the Devil knows that if he can but keep them from believing, they can never attain whatever their preſſing be: And this is the devils work to deſtroy the faith, &amp; then ſet people on working; yet to confound thyſelf, thou ſaith in pag. 114. <hi>Let every one that hath this hope in him, purifie himſelf as Christ is pure.</hi> Yet thou goes on to <hi>thou,</hi> and <hi>thee,</hi> and for this would accuſe as Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees becauſe we uſe it to a ſingle perſon; and in this thou confounds thy ſelf as in the reſt: Firſt, Thou confeſſeſt it to be the moſt proper, and that the Scripture uſeth it therefore; and when thou haſt done, thou ſayeſt thoſe that ſpeak it in this Nation ſeem to be barbarous: ſo that by thy confeſſion, he that ſpeaks proper to you is a Barbarian, yet muſt we be condemned who ſpeak properly, and you juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who have loſt your proper underſtanding through your pride and heatheniſh cuſtoms: and with ſuch confuſed ſtuff as this thou proves us the moſt danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people in the world; but ſayeſt thou, <hi>Thou is to me as You, provided it be not made a matter of Religion, hut if it be, then</hi> thou <hi>abhors the ignorance from whence it comes.</hi> Herein ſhewing thy ſelf to be like thy father, who matters not what men do, ſo that they do it not out of conſcience, but if out of conſcience, then he ahhors that ignorance from whence it comes; for a tender conſcience that takes heed to his tongue, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168397:10"/>
devil abhors; for the devil can ſet the tongue on fire, when all members elſe are wearied with his ſervice, provided he make it not matter of Religion what he ſpeaks; but if he be ſo preciſe that he make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of every idle word, the devil abhors him, for he knows that he that offends not in word is a perfect man, ſo able alſo to bridle the whole body. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3. 2. For the devil knows that by your words you ſhall be juſtified, and by them you ſhall be condemned, and for every idle word all muſt anſwer at the Day of Judgement. And this we know, though you have juſtified your ſelves and are yet in your careleſs way without bridle, be ignorant of, whoſe Religion will be found vain, like your vain talk.</p>
            <p>And further, We know your way of ye-ing the proud, and thou-ing the poor to be impurity, though thou falſly ſay the ſcripture uſes that language (thou) to every ſingle perſon for its property and not for its puriry: But what matter what thou ſayes who ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors it as ignorance that teacheth to ſpeak properly as matter of Religion, but had thy Religion reached to the ordering of thy tongue, we had not had ſuch a number of ſhameleſs lyes caſt upon us by thee, as we have in this Book, which indeed is little elſe but a heap of lyes. But this know, that he that ſeemes to be religious and bridleth not his tongue, his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeems to be vain, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
            <p>Thou proceeds to tell of our quaking, and in that like the reſt thou ſhews thy confuſion. In thy 38. p: thou ſayes (but falſly) <hi>It's a way that never came into the heart of God, to bring his people to perfection by:</hi> when all that do declare the way they came to God, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168397:11"/>
quaking or trembling, and all that knew the Word of God trembled at it.</p>
            <p>And in thy 78. pag. thou owns it in the holy men of God (making thy ſelf a lyar) but ſayes it is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from ours. To which I ſay, haſt thou ſeen us both tremble? or how canſt thou make a difference? let the wiſe judge; but that thy buſie minde muſt be medling to ſpeak of that thou knows nought on, that thou might ſhew thy envy &amp; conſuſion; how ſhould thou know trembling, who knows no word but the letter, &amp; abhors that which ſhould guide the tongue, and thereto would limit God for ever, as to matter of converting of people; thou muſt needs caſt out trembling who excludes the Word, and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> the 66. 5.</p>
            <p>Thou mayeſt read thy generationand thy work, and thy judgement alſo; and what thou knows or trembling is ſeen by what thou knows of the Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It would be thy wiſdom to ſtop thy mouth, and ſpeak: not evil of that thou knows not, thou may long read the letter, and call that the word with thy lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ere thou know what the trembling is of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſuch thou hates, as did thy generation in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>Thou proceeds tell of great things in thy imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the letter; and tells of a ſtate of general reconciliation which all the world is recovered to, though not redeemed from any curſe; and tells of a twofold reconciliation, and a twofold redemption, and many ſuch things in thy confuſed minde, which the Scriptures knows not, but knows not one redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption thy ſelf, but art a ſervant of ſatan in lyes and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168397:11"/>
falſe accuſations againſt the innocent, ſuch a redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Devil can profeſs as ſtands in words from the Letter without power and life; had there been no Letter ſuch a profeſſion would have been as is your practice.</p>
            <p>Thou goes about to deſcribe who are the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and thou concludes all who come in after the Jewiſh rites, ſprinking or dipping In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, being exerciſed in Romiſh Ordinances, &amp;c. Theſe are <hi>Rome's</hi> daughters, though they cry, <hi>Out Harlot</hi> againſt their mother; I ſay go one ſtep higher and take in your own tradition (which is neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to letter not ſpirit, neither in call, manner, nor end, as I have divers times proved, and am ready to do as occaſion is offered) and as it is with theirs, out of the true form, ſo is it out of the true power of godlineſs, and brings forth the ſame fruits with the world (if not worſe) ſo that if any will own you for Saints onely becauſe you have been two or three times dipped, or ſprinkled in the water more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have bin, then they may have ſuch <hi>Saints</hi> enough who do make dipping ſo many times, ſome twice, ſome thrice, as a god and ground of ſalvation and of union; but further then that doth differ you from the world, they ſhall never ſee any thing of a godly conformity, and denying the world's cuſtomes, or conſcientious walking, whereby you ſhall be known from other men, unleſs it be that you have got more ſubtilty to oppoſe the truth, being as the head of the image, got a little higher then the reſt; but as envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wicked and bloody as any is this day in the Nations, and would as gladly ſtir up perſecution had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168397:12"/>
you but power, as ſome of your prime Teachers have ſaid to ſome in Authority, <hi>that he had rather a Law was made to take away his life, then that we ſhould bee ſuffered;</hi> and at this day are you ſcattered through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Nation (by your letters) to rake up what filth you can to caſt upon the children of light: And if thou ſay thou art clear, then let this heap of lies out of thy book be witneſs againſt thee, which were they true might ſerve to take away our lives by the Law of the Nation; yea ſuch a heap of wickedneſs as if hell had been raked to bring it up to caſt upon us; of which we are clear before <hi>God,</hi> but you being a people who have declined your principle of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſcience above all others; ſo you who have done it muſt needs exceed all others in miſchief and hatred againſt ſuch as retain God in their conſciences and dare not ſin againſt him; caſting all manner of evil report on tender conſciences, as becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bow to your filthy pride and reſpect of perſons, and give flattering titles to the ſpirit of exaltation in a proud man or woman; therefore by you we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed as Phariſees, and that we deſtroy relations, and deny civil courteſie, as in this thy Book; when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but the devils pride; and if we take heed to our words, and by that which is pure of God in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences order them according to the ſound words of Chriſt Jeſus and the Scriptures, then we ſtrain at a gnat and ſwallow a Cammel; ſo that to ſpeak in the fear of God and in ſound words, ſuch that cannot be reproved, is a great offence to thee; and the cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel we ſwallow, is becauſe we go not ſo often into the water as you do, in obſervance to your tradition,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168397:12"/>
which is neither in power nor form of <hi>Iohn's</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration (whom you would imitate) when you that go into the water come out as full of pride, envy, covetouſneſs and all manner of wickedneſs as you go in, and the Devil hardned in many of you in lying againſt the truth, onely thereby being conceited that your ſins are waſhed away, though when you are proved none more impudent and brazened in their wickedneſs then you are; witneſs the heap of lies in thy book, which the heathen that never had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion would be aſhamed ſo falſly to utter, as will be ſeen now when thou art put in plainneſs to prove them.</p>
            <p>Nay, were you not ſtark blinde, and drunk with rage againſt the truth, you might once look back, &amp; ſee your ſelves and what you are doing, and how you have dealt with the Lord, who once had betruſted a meaſure of ſimplicity to ſome of you which kept you tender, which you have betrayed above all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Nation; was there not a time when you durſt not have conformed to the world pride and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy manners, their faſhions and cuſtoms now main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, their falſe worſhips? was it not once with you that you could not uſe the worlds Language, as to their corruption therein upheld, and that out of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of conſcience? Was there not once in you a principle againſt lying and falſe accuſing, and perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for conſcience ſake? Then was you hated of the world as you now joyne with the world to hate us and belye us; nay, what thing is it now that your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will ſtrain at? but you can ſwallow, rather then ſuffer perſecution, reproach or loſs of gain;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168397:13"/>
Have not you been witneſs againſt the Miniſtry of the Nations to be of the whore, and their tythes and hire, till a great part of the moſt eminent of you be got into the ſame living out of which you have thruſt them: let England and Ireland witneſs, though I wil not ſay you are all guilty in this particular, for all have not been proved therein; but with what a face you can at this day call the Miniſtery of the Nations whoriſh, and then take the benefit of it your ſelves, or maintain it in others, leſt you ſhould ſuffer the croſs of Chriſt, let all who have the uſe of a good conſcience judge. And you who can ſwallow all this and much more that might be named, contrary to your faith as you call it, and once contrary to your conſcience when it was not ſeared; Is it like that we ſhould be owned by you in making conſcience of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word? or can you do any otherwiſe but abhor it, who have thus made ſhipwrack in your ſelves? and this is the fruits you have brought forth ſince you have ſet your ſelves againſt the Light of the Spirit which led into tenderneſs, and have ſet up the Letter for the Light; and ſo being become heart-blinde, are you grown paſt feeling, into open lying and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as at this day it is ſeen and lamented.</p>
            <p>And now do not ſay this is railing accuſation and hard terms which is truth, but let the light of Chriſt which you thus hate, ſearch your hearts, and paſs judgement upon you, and own it before the Lord and all the world, and give praiſe to the Son from whom the Light comes, for you have nothing elſe will let you ſee your hearts and the deſperate wickedneſs that lodgeth therein; it's the light that muſt ſearch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168397:13"/>
it out, and reveal it to you, and not the Letter: you may read in the Letter what deceit was in other mens hearts; but it muſt be within you that lets you ſee your own, the eye of God it is muſt let you ſee and ſearch the dark corners thereof, which is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wicked, and you know it not but by the light of the world, which lets all the world ſee their deceits (who doth but minde it) which light is that the <hi>God</hi> of this world hates, and above all would blind that eye, for which end all his inſtruments are now at work (as is manifeſt) to make ſhipwrack of Faith that is held in a pure conſcience, and you in the head thereof; of which you muſt repent and returne to you firſt tenderneſs, wherein you was once growing out of the elements and rudiments of the world, to be led by the ſpirit of the Lamb where ever he goes; and not by ſhadows which are left deſolate, becauſe of the wickedneſs of ſuch as have lived therein: and look upon circumciſion, for the continuance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Jewes had more from the Letter then you have for your way of carnal water; for it was ſaid it ſhould be a ſign for ever, but ſo was it not ſaid of Water-baptiſm, but the contrary; and minde what a generation was left in circumciſion, when Chriſt led out by his <hi>Spirit</hi> from that Ordinance, a company of envious murtherers, lyars, and falſe accuſers, who ſet themſelves againſt the way and light of Chriſt, to devour all that followed his light, againſt whom they pretended the Letter, and thought they did right, and ſo do to this day; and were you not wholly blinde you might read your ſelves herein, and what hath befallen you ſince you ſet your ſelves
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168397:14"/>
to this work? every day hardneſs and more blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, till you be much more mad in miſchief then they was, and more blinde; for they fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light becauſe it led out of their traditions which was after the letter; but yon oppoſe the light when it leads to the ſound words in the letter, and calls it <hi>Phariſaical,</hi> and ſelf-righteouſueſs, or any fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Name to make it odious, and abhors it if it be but done in following the Spirit; ſo that to follow the ſpiritual Light of Chriſt is abhorred by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his inſtruments, though it be in that which they confeſs is proper, and uſed in the letter, (which they ſay is their Word) witneſs thy 57. and 58. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>And yet with all this wickedneſs and blindneſs (and much more) the like unchriſtian carriage in your fore-head, would you binde all to fall down to your tradition you have ſet up, and worſhip that or elſe no Chriſtians nor ſalvation, but all the filth of hell muſt be raked up and caſt upon their godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, for no other thing, but becauſe we cannot cry up that for ſalvation which cannot ſave you (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs how you are ſaved from theſe wickedneſſes who worſhip before it) further then in your imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, believing that obeying that Ordinance, as you call it, you muſt be ſaved from hell when you are dead; but to be ſaved from theſe wicked wayes while you live, you never believe, nor doth your god teach any ſuch faith; ſo they that are blinde may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the leading of Chriſt in Spirit, and follow your ſhadow, which can neither ſave you nor them.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168397:14"/>
But if you would have all to worſhip what you have ſet up (your called ordinance) let it appear to all men what is therein mighty to ſave; Is there ſome better<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs betwixt being a captive to the devil in ſin under your water, and being a captive to ſin under the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Teachers water, being both out of the true way declared in Scripture, only yours a little nearer in the letter, but both one in Spirit &amp; Power, led captive at his wil who rules in them &amp; you, who are diſobedient to the ſpiritual Light of Chriſt; wil your water ſave you more then theirs when you both are unwaſhed from your ſin, and live in rebellion againſt God? doth your Ordinance then ſave you?</p>
            <p>But doth it not appear to all the children of light, that you are in the ſtate of the Jews, who cryed, the Temple, the Temple when God was deparred; then they that was left in it was become abominable to God, that which was the houſe of God formerly, was then become a den of thieves, and murderers, and liars; yet was they as zealous for their. Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as you are for your water, and had as plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yea, and their Ordinances was in the right form and call, whereas yours are not as any of the Saints did ever practice in Scripture declared; ſo if you be not ſtark blinde, read your ſelves and repent, and think not to ſay, The Ordinances, the Ordinances, when you are both out of form and power; for if we muſt believe you for ſo ſaying, why not the Prieſts alſo who cry the ſame with you, both taken on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true form, life or power, this we may not do, who have heard and learned of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168397:15"/>But this I ſay to thee, and the reſt that are joined with thee herein, If he be a God you would have us all to bow to, let us ſee what a God he is, whether it be the God of Righteouſneſs, or the God of this world and Deceit, firſt let us ſee that by your Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances thou thy ſelf be led to repentance, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs all thy damnable heap of lies thou haſt caſt on us in thy book in envie againſt the light, and that as openly as thou haſt ſlandered; alſo repent of thy falſe Doctrine I have proved which thou haſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and decline thy errors therein. And all the reſt of you, deny your ſelves and the world and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to Chriſt; leave your filthy pride and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and abominable conformity to men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt mindes, for advantage reſpecting mens perſons and maintaining their abominable worſhips and worſhippers therein.</p>
            <p>And you that ſay you are Miniſters, prove your ſelves in all things as the Miniſters of Chriſt in wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, in faſtings, in wandrings, hunger and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, having no certain dwelling place; in tumults of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; in neceſſities; in ſtripes; in whipping, mocking, ſtoning and impriſonment, &amp;c. Let us ſee if it be your manner to diſpute in the Idols-Temple againſt their Idols-worſhip that deceives ſouls; and preach in the ſtreets and markets daily, &amp;c. and all this freely without hire. Theſe are the Apoſtles wayes, and this is the Apoſtles word; let us ſee if you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted according to it, and that your God is the ſame theirs was, and will carry you forth in the ſame way and work, and that you dare truſt him therein: And as we ſee you in the Apoſtles works, ſo we ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168397:15"/>
be engaged to believe that you are converted by their Word, which was before the letter was, and the light thereof in all conſciences will confeſs to you; and that this is the living God whoſe wayes is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous that you preach for all to worſhip; and then we ſhall own you, and the Apoſtles words will own you and your practice, but where you are now we cannot; nor can we worſhip with you that for God that which cannot ſave you from that wicked lying ſpirit that acts you, nor lead you into the ſame work that it hath done all his Miniſters in all ages; for we know that God, whoſe Word is Righteouſneſs, and his wayes Truth, and what Ordinances he ſets up, that will we worſhip in, for thoſe Ordinances are ſpiritual and have life in them, wherein God dwells, and in them by him we ſhall be kept. And the clear water we know, wherein our bodies are waſhed; and the blood of cleanſing, and the bread of life, which was broken for us and is given to us, by which we live, and own the Apoſtles practices, to follow Chriſt in our meaſures, for which we are counted the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of all things unto this day; and till then think not that we ſhall worſhip your tradition which brings forth a lye that cannot ſave the Founder; for that wherein God dwells not, is but a likeneſs, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and ſo your practice proves your way whereof it is.</p>
            <p>Surely in vain do you ſetup Idols; the Lord is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, your carved Images are lighter then vanity: All the idols of the heathen are void of Righteouſneſs, truth is wanting in their inward parts; they have deckt them with colours, they have covered them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168397:16"/>
with words; they cry, <hi>Come bow and worſhip,</hi> but doth not conſider that a lye is in there right hand; there is none that conſidereth once to ſay in himſelf, <hi>What is this that I am doing? What profit is there in that to which I fall down? is this the living God for whom I am thus contending that is not able to plead for himſelf, and defend himſelf with righteouſneſs; with judgement, and equity, to plead againſt his enemies in their own hearts? that cannot ſtrike thorow the loynes of his adverſaries, &amp; cover me with innocency and peace, while he covers his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies with confuſion? Is this he whoſe Word endureth for ever, from generation to generation, who hath left me to ſeek counſel in the Letter and without his Spirit, and to conſult with men how to keep up his Ordinances, and to go to carnal weapons to avenge him on them who caſt down his Altars, who cut down his Groves, and declares againſt the way of his worſhips.</hi> Oh fooliſh people, is this he that pleads the cauſe of his people, who cannot plead for himſelf in Judgement, nor for you in Righteouſneſs? Let him put ſpiritual weapons into your hands; let him fill your hearts with Righteouſneſs, and your wayes with equity; let him cover you with innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and preſerve you in patience, till he have made your light to ſhine in darkneſs, that therewith he may confound his Enemies; let him cauſe truth to ſpring in the earth, and faith to bud and bloſſom, that righteouſneſs may cover you from the ſtorm, and the effect thereof may be peace: then ſhall all your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies be aſhamed and confounded before you; for his power ſhall paſs before you to make the earth to tremble at his preſence, whom the carnal ſees not; let it be proclaimed before him, The Lord our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168397:16"/>
gracious and full of mercy, whoſe eye goes thorow the world, and who will by no means clear the guilty: And if this be the Name of your God, let it be written upon you; let the Zeal thereof be as a mark in your fore-heads, and his sighteouſneſs upon you as a Breſt-plate, that all may ſay, this is the Lord, bow before him, there is no other; who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his people lights in whom he holds forth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and healing to the Nations: Surely this is the Lord, and this is work, and to him ſhall the world bow, and his Saints confeſs his Name for ever.</p>
            <p>Verily in the Lord our God is ſalvation &amp; ſtrength; Righteouſneſs is thy right Name, Judgement goes before thy face to confound thine Enemies; thy light is as a fire to conſume the wicked, and by the ſame is thy Word declared; therewith thou ſends the rich a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way empty, but the poor thou ſatisfies with goodneſs everlaſting: thou hides thy way from the ſubtil, that thou mayeſt ſet the Priſoner out of the Pit; that he may poſſeſs the gates of his Enemies, and go in and out and feed in ſafety: thou makes him ſtrong that was feeble, but ſtrikes through the loins of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: thou dries up the depths of the ſea that thy ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed ones may paſs over. Our enemies ſees and are troubled, rage hath ſeiſed upon them; in travells they are with miſchief, they are pained to bring forth and their birth is a lye. Their ſon cannot ſave them; they have brought forth darkneſs and folly: Counſel and peace is not in him, therefore they ſtagger in Judgement: but thou Lord God gives us light as in the beginning: the ancient of dayes is our ſtability, things of many generations haſt thou ſet before us:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168397:17"/>
the foundation that is unmoveable is diſcovered therein: thou haſt ſet us as upon a Rock, ſo that the Floods of the ungodly cannot move us: thou haſt lifted up an Enſigne, and the Heathen are angry, the pride of the Nations hath gathered againſt thee: thou haſt ſet up judgment againſt them in the ſtreets of wickedneſs, and hath ſent out the Lamb amongſt the Beaſt of the field, upon his head thou haſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a defence, thou haſt covered him with righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as with a garment: thou haſt covered thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with thick darkneſs, and their Armies with a cloud, they grope at noon-day: thou haſt ſmitten the horſe with blindneſs and his rider with madneſs: they have riſen up againſt thee, they are confounded: they are driven back, their arm hath failed, and thou ſaveſt thy people with a mighty ſalvation: the meek ſees it and rejoice, it glads the ſoul of the innocent to ſee thee. <hi>Praiſe our God in the beauty of holineſs, all that are come to the peaceable habitation: Sing unto the Lord a new Song, you people of good underſtanding, who knows the root of righteouſneſs where it ſprings, and are fed with the dew of heaven, whoſe hearts the Lord hath opened for himſelf, that he may fill you with goodneſs, that you may bring forth as a watered garden, that the Lord may take delight in his own, and dwell in you for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
